<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<search>
  
  
  
  <entry>
    <title>What&#39;s true understanding?</title>
    <link href="/2026/02/02/what_true_understanding/"/>
    <url>/2026/02/02/what_true_understanding/</url>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>Recently I’ve taken a class in UoA called “Self-Leadership”, which has given me a great deal of food for thought. It was somewhat novel and unfamiliar to me, and I mistook it for a typical self-success course.<br>But the course content turned out to be surprisingly insightful. I’ve learned the most fundamental practice of self-leadership: <strong>reflection</strong>. There is no secret formula or magic behind it. It simply offers me a quiet chance to pause, slow down, and reflect on my inner self.</p></blockquote><h2 id="TL-DR"><a href="#TL-DR" class="headerlink" title="TL;DR"></a><em>TL;DR</em></h2><ul><li>The illusion of understanding is a common trap in learning, where we feel like we understand something but lack genuine mastery.</li><li>Use Feynman’s Method to check if you understand the concept.</li></ul><h2 id="Observation"><a href="#Observation" class="headerlink" title="Observation"></a>Observation</h2><p>These days I spent plenty of time diving into <a href="https://csapp.cs.cmu.edu//">CSAPP</a>, a classic book in computer science. Over the past few years in my work, I always intended to read this book thoroughly, but never got around to it.</p><p>What I found interesting is that I acted differently. I somehow took on two distinct approaches once I began learning basic concepts such as <code>Virtual Memory</code> and <code>Set Associative Caches</code>.</p><p>To summarize, I understand <code>Set Associative Caches</code> better than <code>Virtual Memory</code>. Meanwhile, reading the chapter on <code>Virtual Memory</code> felt more enjoyable and rewarding. In contrast, studying the other topic is quite challenging and “full of dopamine”.</p><h2 id="Inflection"><a href="#Inflection" class="headerlink" title="Inflection"></a>Inflection</h2><p><strong>Why?</strong><br>It is an issue with the <strong>illusion of understanding</strong>. It is <strong>recognition</strong>, yet not genuine mastery.</p><p>When I closed the book, and looked back at the whole picture of <code>Virtual Memory</code>. I asked myself, but I got stuck over and over again. I couldn’t clarify the details of the concept, and I came up with some new questions. It ended up the knowledge is like a cyclone, it comes and goes, leaving a mess.</p><p>I think the reason is that I used to use <code>Virtual Memory</code> a lot in my work. Therefore, I just read the concepts happily without stop thinking more about it. There was a voice in mind said “Yeah, that’s it. The layout is just like that. The underlying mechanism is just like that.”. I was so satisfied that I had learnt so much <em>again</em>. (Maybe after several days, I could be “happy” once more). 😔</p><p>In terms of <code>Set Associative Caches</code>, it’s not a huge knowledge, so I break it down into smaller parts and draw diagrams to help me understand it better. I somehow map the diagrams in my mind, and start explaining it to myself. Every time I get stuck by something that I can’t make it clear, I just go back to the book and read it again. Eventually, I really master it! I can spot connections between it and my existing knowledge. 😁</p><h2 id="Implication-Action"><a href="#Implication-Action" class="headerlink" title="Implication &amp;&amp; Action"></a>Implication &amp;&amp; Action</h2><p>I may have tried these methods consciously or unconsciously before. But now I need to define them clearly and supervise myself to see if I can put them into practice 👊.</p><ol><li>Thinking about how to articulate the ideas without opening the book. Actually it’s <strong><a href="https://subjectguides.york.ac.uk/study-revision/feynman-technique">Feynman’s Method</a></strong>. Personally, I can understand about 90% of new knowledge after using the <code>Feynman Method</code>.</li><li><strong>Drawing diagrams</strong> to help me understand the concepts better.</li><li><strong>Break down</strong> the knowledge into smaller parts, making it easier to take action.</li></ol><h2 id="Attachment"><a href="#Attachment" class="headerlink" title="Attachment"></a>Attachment</h2><p>Here’s the Pros. and Cons. of using Feynman’s Method, just for you information.</p><p><img src="/images/feynman.png" alt="Feynman&#39;s Method"></p>]]></content>
    
    
    <categories>
      
      <category>Everyday Reflection</category>
      
    </categories>
    
    
  </entry>
  
  
  
  
</search>
